Back home, my friends call me nicknames,
في موطني يُطلق عليّ أصدقائي عدّة ألقاب
such as "The Giant Clam Girl,"
مثل "فتاة المحّار العملاق"
"Clam Queen,"
"ملكة المحّار"
or, "The Mother of Clams."
أو "أم المحّارات".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is because every time I see them,
هذا لأنني في كل مرة أرى فيها المحّار
I talk nonstop about giant clams all day,
أتكلم عنهم بلا توقف طوال اليوم،
every day.
كل يوم.
Giant clams are these massive and colorful shelled marine animals,
المحّارات العملاقة كائنات بحرية ضخمة ذات صدفات ملونة،
the largest of its kind.
الأكبر في فصيلتها.
Just look at this shell.
فقط انظروا إلى هذه الصدفة.
The biggest recorded individual was four-and-a-half-feet long
أكبر محّار مُسجّل يصل طوله إلى 4 أقدام ونصف
and weighed about 550 pounds.
ويزن حوالي 550 باوند.
That is almost as heavy as three baby elephants.
هذا يعادل تقريبًا وزن ثلاثة من صغار الفيلة.
South Pacific legends once described giant clams as man-eaters
تصف أساطير منطقة جنوب المحيط الهادئ المحّارات العملاقة على أنها آكلات للبشر
that would lie in wait on the seabed to trap unsuspecting divers.
وبأنها تقبع في قاع البحار بانتظار الانقضاض على الغواصين غير المدركين لهذا الخطر.
A story goes that a diver had lost his legs
هنالك قصة تحكي عن غوّاص فقد ساقيه
while trying to retrieve a pearl from a giant clam.
أثناء محاولته استخراج لؤلؤة من محّار عملاق.
I thought, "Really?"
تساءلت "حقًا؟"
So out of curiosity,
لذلك بدافع الفضول
I did an experiment using myself as bait.
قمت بتجربة مُستخدمةً نفسي كطُعم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I carefully placed my hand into the clam's mouth and waited.
وضعت يدي بحذر داخل فم المحّار وانتظرت.
Hmm ...
اممم...
I still have my hand.
ما تزال يدي موجودة.
It seems that these gentle giants would rather retreat
يبدو أنّ هذه الحيوانات اللطيفة تفضل الانسحاب
and protect their fleshy bodies
وحماية أجسادها الطرية
than feed on me.
بدلًا من التغذّي عليّ.
So much for those killer clam myths!
الكثير من الأساطير عن هذا المحّار القاتل!
Unfortunately, the reality is,
للأسف الحقيقة هي
we are the giant clams' biggest threat.
أننّا نحن نُمثل التهديد الأكبر للمحّار العملاق.
Considered a delicacy throughout the Western Pacific and Indian Oceans,
باعتبار طعمه الشهي، في غرب المحيط الهادئ والمحيط الهندي
giant clams have been traditionally fished as seafood.
يتم اصطياد المحّارات العملاقة عادة كنوع من الطعام البحري.
Fishermen are particularly interested in their adductor muscles,
يهتم الصيادون بشكل خاص بعضلات المحّار المُقرِّبة،
which are organs that hold the two shells together like a hinge.
وهي العضلة التي تُمسك بالصدفتين معًا على شكل مفصل.
Just for their muscles,
فقط من أجل عضلاتها،
giant clams were almost hunted to extinction
كان يتم اصطياد المحّارات العملاقة حتى كادت تنقرض
between the 1960s and 1980s.
بين ستينيات وثمانينيات القرن الماضي.
Clamshells are also popular in the ornamental trade
صدف المحّار شائع أيضًا في تجارة الزخارف
as jewelry and for display.
كمجوهرات ومن أجل عرضها.
In the South China Sea,
في بحر الصين الجنوبي
fishermen went out of their way to collect fossilized clamshells
يذهب الصيادون لجمع أصداف المحّار المُتحجرة
by digging through large areas of coral reefs.
عن طريق الحفر في مناطق واسعة من الشعب المرجانية.
These were later carved and sold as so-called "ivory handicrafts" in China.
فيما بعد يٌنقش عليهم ثم يتم بيعهم في الصين تحت مسمى "أعمال يدوية عاجيّة".
Giant clams, dead or alive, are not safe from us.
المحّارات العملاقة سواء كانت ميّتة أو حيّة ليست بأمان منا.
It's a "clamity!"
إنها "كارثة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
With the spotlight on more charismatic marine animals
مع إلقاء الضوء على المزيد من الحيوانات البحرية الساحرة
such as the whales and coral reefs,
مثل الحيتان والشعب المرجانية
it is easy to forget that other marine life needs our help, too.
من السهل نسيان أن حيوانات بحرية أخرى بحاجة لمساعدتنا أيضًا.
My fascination with giant clams got me started on conservation research
دفعني إعجابي بالمحّارات العملاقة للبدء بأبحاث وقائية
to fill in the knowledge gaps on their ecology and behavior.
لملء ثغرات معرفتنا عن بيئتهم وتصرفاتهم.
One of the discoveries that we made was that giant clams could walk
إحدى اكتشافاتنا كانت أن المحّارات العملاقة بإمكانها المشي
across the seafloor.
عبر قاع البحر.
Yes, you heard me right:
نعم ما سمعتموه صحيح,
they can walk.
بإمكانهم المشي.
To find out,
لاكتشاف ذلك
we placed numerous baby clams on a grid.
قمنا بوضع الكثير من صغار المحّار على شبكة.
Now watch what happens over 24 hours.
و الآن شاهدوا ماذا حدث خلال 24 ساعة.
We think that walking is important for getting away from predators
نعتقد أن المشي ضروري للهرب من الحيوانات المُفترسة
and finding mates for breeding.
ولإيجاد زوج من أجل التكاثر.
While it can hard to imagine any movement in these enormous animals,
بالرغم من صعوبة تخيل قيام هذه الحيوانات الضخمة بأيّة حركة
giant clams up to 400 pounds can still walk,
فإنّ المحّارات العملاقة والتي يصل وزنها حتى 400 باوند باستطاعتها المشي،
they just move slower.
هم فقط يتحركون بشكل أبطأ.
During my PhD, I discovered more secrets about the giant clams.
أثناء تحضيري للدكتوراه اكتشفت المزيد من الأسرار عن المحّارات العملاقة.
But there was something missing in my work.
لكن كان هنالك شيء ما ناقص في عملي.
I found myself asking,
وجدت نفسي أتساءل،
"Why should people care about conserving giant clams?" --
"لماذا يجب على الناس الاهتمام بحماية المحّارات العملاقة؟"
other than myself, of course.
بخلاف نفسي، طبعًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It turns out that giant clams have a giant impact on coral reefs.
اتّضح أن للمحّارات العملاقة أثر كبير على الشعب المرجانية.
These multitasking clams are reef builders,
هذه المحّارات مُتعددة المهام بنّاءة للشعب المرجانية،
food factories,
مصانع للطعام،
shelters for shrimps and crabs
ملاجئ للقُريدس والسلطعون،
and water filters,
ومصفاة للمياه،
all rolled into one.
كل هذا جُمع في شيء واحد.
In a nutshell,
باختصار،
giant clams play a major contributing role
تلعب المحّارات العملاقة دورًا رئيسيًّا فعالًا
as residents of their own reef home,
كسكان لشعبهم المرجانية الخاصة،
and just having them around keeps the reef healthy.
ومجرد وجودهم فقط يساهم في إبقاء الشعب المرجانية صحيّة.
And because they can live up to 100 years old,
ولأن بإمكانهم العيش حتى 100 عام،
giant clams make vital indicators of coral reef health.
فإنهم يكونون بمثابة مؤشرات حيوية عن مدى صحّة الشعب المرجانية.
So when giant clams start to disappear from coral reefs,
لذلك عندما تبدأ المحّارات العملاقة بالاختفاء من الشعب المرجانية،
their absence can serve as an alarm bell
فإن غيابهم يمكن أن يمثل جرس إنذار
for scientists to start paying attention,
لاسترعاء انتباه العلماء،
similar to the canary in a coal mine.
وهذا شبيه بعمل طائر الكناري في منجم الفحم.
But giant clams are endangered.
لكن المحّارات العملاقة معرضة للخطر.
The largest clam in the world is facing the threat of extinction,
يواجه أكبر محّار في العالم خطر الانقراض،
with more than 50 percent of the wild population severely depleted.
مع أكثر من 50% من محّارات البرية مُستنزفين بشدّة.
And the ecological benefits of having giant clams on coral reefs
والمنافع البيئية من وجود المحّارات العملاقة في الشعب المرجانية
are likely to continue only if populations are healthy,
من المرجح استمرارها فقط إذا كان تعدادهم صحّيًّا،
making their conservation paramount.
مما يجعل حمايتهم أمرًا مهمًا جدًّا.
So I stand here today to give a voice to the giant clams,
لذا أقف هنا اليوم لأمنح صوتًا للمحارات العملاقة
because I care a whole lot for these amazing animals,
لأنني أهتم كثيرًا بشأن هذه الحيوانات المذهلة
and they deserve to be cared for.
وهم يستحقون هذا الاهتمام.
It is time for the giant clams to step out of their shells,
آن أوان خروج المحّارات العملاقة من صدفها
and show the world that they, too, can be the heroes of the oceans.
ليُروا العالم أن بإمكانهم هم أيضًا أن يكونوا أبطال المحيطات.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)